Richard D. Butterfield Slide and Photograph Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Richard D. Butterfield Slide and Photograph Collection
1952-1984
VRC 175
Yale University Arts Library
17.75
46 boxes
Collection consists of photographs and slides taken by R. D. Butterfield from 1952-1983, and donated to the Visual Resources Collection at the encouragement of Abbott Lowell Cummings. Most are architectural studies, with particular emphasis on Venice's Grand Canal, Palladio and his influence, New England churches, and churches by Christopher Wren. Mr. Butterfield was a practicing architect, M.Arch. Yale, based in Farmington, CT. He died in 1986. Mr. Butterfield was interested in comparisons between British and European architecture and New England architecture, and had an exhibit at the New Britain Museum of American Art in 1983, "Towers From-The-Ground-Up," on that subject. The exhibit is thoroughly documented in this collection. Palladio's influence on American architecture is also explored, as is Wren's. All slides have been carefully labeled according to Mr. Butterfield's numbering system, and his slide index is enclosed with the collection in Box 26. Many of them are also briefly identified on the slide mounts. The photos are of very high quality, although some of the film has faded. The index details the year the photo was taken, the subject, the camera and film, and sometimes even the time of day.
Butterfield, Richard D., -1986
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of photographs and slides taken by R. D. Butterfield from 1952-1983, and donated to the Visual Resources Collection at the encouragement of Abbott Lowell Cummings. Most are architectural studies, with particular emphasis on Venice's Grand Canal, Palladio and his influence, New England churches, and churches by Christopher Wren.
Mr. Butterfield was a practicing architect, M.Arch. Yale, based in Farmington, CT. He died in 1986. Mr. Butterfield was interested in comparisons between British and European architecture and New England architecture, and had an exhibit at the New Britain Museum of American Art in 1983, "Towers From-The-Ground-Up," on that subject. The exhibit is thoroughly documented in this collection. Palladio's influence on American architecture is also explored, as is Wren's.
All slides have been carefully labeled according to Mr. Butterfield's numbering system, and his slide index is enclosed with the collection in Box 26. Many of them are also briefly identified on the slide mounts. The photos are of very high quality, although some of the film has faded. The index details the year the photo was taken, the subject, the camera and film, and sometimes even the time of day.
Arrangement
Related material is grouped together, and as much as possible, remains in Mr. Butterfield's original order. See below for a detailed listing. It is recommended that anyone using these slides also recall Box 26, which contains Butterfield's slide index.
Architecture; Photographs; Reproductions
- Butterfield Collection (Box 1)
  General
  (ca. 14,900 35mm slides, 414 70mm slides, 52 sets of paired 70mm slides, 696 photographs, 52 contact sheets with corresponding negatives, 66 sheets of negatives without contact sheets)
  - Slide boxes: A-AB (ca. 150 35mm slides) (Box 1)
    21 boxes. From box marked "Edited. Some boxes to Bryce." Slides appear to be leftovers, and mostly from ca. 1952. All boxes have full identification noted on the outsides. Many of these photos are family snapshots, building sites, etc.
  - Slide boxes: AC-BX (ca. 360 35mm slides) (Box 2)
    24 boxes. From box marked "Edited. Some boxes to Bryce." Slides are from 1952-1953. All boxes have full identification noted on the outsides. Many of these photos are family snapshots, building sites, etc.
  - Slide boxes: BY-DC (ca. 450 35mm slides) (Box 3)
    26 boxes. From box marked "Edited. Some boxes to Bryce." Slides are from 1953-1954. All boxes have full identification noted on the outsides. Many of these photos are family photos, building sites, etc.
  - Slide boxes: EA-FD (ca. 35mm 480 slides) (Box 4)
    24 boxes. All boxes have full identification noted on the outsides. Slides are from 1954. Many of these photos are family photos, building sites, etc.
  - Slide boxes: FE-FZ, LB-LQ (ca. 420 35mm slides) (Box 5)
    21 boxes. All boxes have full identification noted on the outsides. Slides are from 1954, 1955, 1957. Many of these photos are family photos, building sites, etc.
  - Slide boxes: LQ, LS, LY, ZU-ZY (ca. 300 35mm slides) (Box 6)
    12 boxes. Slides are from 1957 (family photos), 1964 (London). There are also two boxes of slides culled from various rolls of South Carolina, New York, Minnesota, and Maryland.
  - Slide boxes: AAA-AAV (ca. 325 35mm slides) (Box 7)
    13 boxes. Slides are from 1964, and include architecture of Paris, Meudon, London, Florence, S. Gimignano, Siena, and Rome.
  - Slide boxes: AAW-ACE (ca. 420 35mm slides) (Box 8)
    14 boxes. Slides are from 1964 and 1965, and include architecture of Rome, Sorrento, Paestum, London, and Cambridge.
  - Slide boxes: ACF-ADC (ca. 400 35mm slides) (Box 9)
    13 boxes. Slides are from 1965-1966, and include architecture of Cambridge, London, Venice, Paris, Chartres.
  - Slide boxes: 154-186 (ca. 620 35mm slides) (Box 10)
    26 boxes. Slides are from 1968-1969, and include personal photos, New England, English church prints, Rome, and Venice.
  - Slide boxes: 187-203 (ca. 510 35mm slides) (Box 11)
    17 boxes. Slides are from 1969, and include architecture from Rome, Venice, and the beginning of London.
  - Slides boxes: 204-218 (ca. 500 35mm slides) (Box 12)
    15 boxes. All Slides are from 1969, and include personal photos and various cities and towns in Britain.
  - Slides boxes: 219-258 (ca. 600 35mm slides) (Box 13)
    26 boxes. All Slides are from 1969-1970, and include personal photos, construction sites, and New England buildings.
  - Slides boxes: 259-273 (ca. 400 35mm slides) (Box 14)
    15 boxes. Slides are from 1970, and include Venice, Portofino, Nice, and other scenes from Southern France.
  - Slides boxes: 274-287 (ca. 500 35mm slides) (Box 15)
    14 boxes. Slides are from 1970, and include Southern France, various chateaux, Versailles, and the return to the United States.
  - Slides boxes: 331-336 (ca. 450 35mm slides) (Box 16)
    11 boxes. Slides are from 1971, and are of architecture in Britain, and a box culled from various rolls labeled "Venice Project."
  - Slides boxes: 337-355 (ca. 510 35mm slides) (Box 17)
    17 boxes. Slides are from 1971, and include personal photos, architecture in Winchester, London, and various other locations in Britain, and Venice.
  - Slides boxes: 356-382 (ca. 475 35mm slides) (Box 18)
    22 boxes. Slides are from 1971-1972, and include personal photos, job sites, and New England architecture.
  - Slides boxes: 383-403, 500-506 (ca. 450 35mm slides) (Box 19)
    20 boxes. Slides are from 1972-1974 and 1981, and include personal photos, job sites, and New England architecture.
  - Slides boxes: 508-530 (ca. 450 35mm slides) (Box 20)
    18 boxes. Slides are from 1981-1982, and include architecture in Virginia, New England, and Christopher Wren churches in Oxford and London.
  - Slides boxes: 531-550 (ca. 410 35mm slides) (Box 21)
    20 boxes. Slides are from 1982, and include architecture in New England and London.
  - Slides boxes: 551-552, 613-685 (ca. 380 35mm slides) (Box 22)
    18 boxes. Slides are from 1982-1983 and 1985, and include personal photos, architecture in London, Venice, other places in Britain, and New England.
  - Slides boxes: 688-697 (ca. 525 35mm slides) (Box 23)
    9 boxes. Slides are from 1985, and include architecture in New England.
  - Slides boxes: 49-78 (ca. 575 35mm slides) (Box 24)
    25 boxes. Slides are from 1967-1968, and include personal photos and job sites. These slides do not seem to be listed in detail in Mr. Butterfield's catalogue.
- Palladian Windows I (Box 25)
  (245 35mm slides, 46 prints)
  5 double slide cartridges, slides in order, and slides listed on cartridge exterior.
  - Four Centuries of "Palladian Windows" (mostly U.S.A.) (100 slides) (Box 25)
  - Four Centuries of "Palladian Windows" (mostly Europe) (100 slides) (Box 25)
  - Façades and Palladian Windows (100 slides) (Box 25)
  - Palladian Windows in Re: Church Architecture (77 slides) (other slots are taken (Box 25)
    by markers indicating which slides are to be used there from the "Four Centuries" boxes)
  - Palladian Windows Miscellaneous and more Façades and Palladian Windows (66 slides) (Box 25)
- Palladian Windows II (Box 26)
  2 double slide cartridges, slides in order, numbered according to Mr. Butterfield's system, except where noted.
  - Palladio (77 slides) (half of these are purchased from Centro Internazionale di Studi di Architettura A. Palladio, Vicenza, and are badly faded). (Box 26)
  - More Palladian Stuff and Millar (60 slides) (includes some purchased slides, badly faded) (Box 26)
  - 1 box of slides (208 slides), removed from a binder, numbered (Box 26)
    - U.S.A. Palladian Windows (Box 26)
  - 2 Notebooks of mounted photographic prints (Box 26)
    - Façades with Palladian Windows (32 8x10 in. prints) (Box 26)
      (does not seem to repeat slide cartridges in box 26, most photos labeled only on the backs, where it's concealed by the mounting)
    - Palladio etc. (14 8x10 in. prints, some faded) (Box 26)
- Butterfield Slide Index (Box 26)
  (1 notebook)
- Palladian Windows III (Box 27)
  (97 prints, one folder of notes, essays, and clippings)
  - 2 Notebooks of mounted photographic prints (Box 27)
    - Four Centuries of "Palladian Windows" etc (Box 27)
      (Meaning Innovations not Conceived by Palladio) (48 8x10 in.prints, labeled and annotated, includes purchased prints and illustrations)
    - Palladian Window Details (Box 27)
      (15 8x10 in.prints, most labeled and annotated)
  - Four Centuries of "Palladian Windows" essay and diagrams (two copies) (Box 27)
  - Palladian Windows slides and text (folder with slide notes, essay, clippings) (Box 27)
  - Folder of 17 8x10 in. black & white prints of related material (Box 27)
  - Folder of color prints (17 4x7 in., 4 8x10 in., faded to green) (Box 27)
- Venice I (Box 28)
  (1016 35mm slides)
  - Slides of Venice from 1980, 1982, and 1983. (Box 28)
- Venice II (Box 29)
  (400 35mm slides, 84 prints)
  - 2 double slide cartridges, slides in order, and slides listed on cartridge exterior. (Box 29)
    - Churches in Venice (400 slides) (Box 29)
  - 2 Notebooks of black & white prints (Box 29)
    - Byzantine – Gothic (Box 29)
      (48 prints, mounted back to back on board, plus diagram/map of Grand Canal and identification list)
    - Renaissance – Baroque (Box 29)
      (36 prints, mounted back to back on board, plus diagram/map and identification list)
- Venice III (Box 30)
  (62 70mm slides, 33 contact sheets and corresponding negatives)
  - 1 metal box of 70mm slides, undated, either labeled or easily identified (Box 30)
    (taken with a Linhof camera, and unfortunately much faded to pink)
    - Venice I (Box 30)
  - 1 Notebook (Box 30)
    (29 sets of large format contact sheets and negatives, 4 sets of 35mm contact sheets and negatives)
    - Venice 1980 Black & White (Box 30)
- Towers From-The-Ground-Up Exhibit: New Britain Museum of American Art, 1984 (Box 31)
  (395 35mm slides, 3 notebooks, 44 negatives, 79 prints)
  - 1 Notebook of photographs and documentation of the exhibit New Britain Exhibit (Box 31)
  - 2 double slide cartridges, slides in lecture order, numbered, many identified on slide mount. (Box 31)
  - Towers From-The-Ground-Up, Part I: Wren (200 slides) (Box 31)
  - Towers From-The-Ground-Up, Part II: New England (195 slides) (Box 31)
  - 1 Notebook with lecture, slide cues, slide list, and exhibit display list (Box 31)
  - 1 Notebook with correspondence related to Mr. Butterfield's attempt to publish his material on Wren and New England churches. (Box 31)
  - 1 Box of negatives, large format, of images used in the exhibit and of the exhibit display panels themselves (Box 31)
    (prints are in the notebook New Britain Exhibit) (18 2x2 ½ in., 26 4 x 5 in.)
  - 1 Box of 8 x 10 in. prints associated with the exhibit (79 prints) (Box 31)
  - 1 Folder of black & white prints, 11 x 17 in. (25 prints) (Box 32)
- Sub-Consciously or Other-Wise (Box 32)
  (189 35mm slides, 28 prints)
  - 3 double slide cartridges, slides in order, numbered according to Mr. Butterfield's system, many identified on slide mount. (Box 32)
    - Old Buildings with blanks, #1 Old, #2 Old (51 slides) (Box 32)
    - Overflow, #3 Old, #3 New (51 slides) (Box 32)
    - #1 New, #2, Odds and Ends (87 slides) (Box 32)
  - 1 Notebook of prints, with introduction, captions, notes (Box 32)
    - Photographic Comparisons from the File of R.D. Butterfield (28 photos) (Box 32)
- Sub-Consciously or Other-Wise (Box 33)
  (52 pairs of 70mm slides, 6 single slides)
  - 2 boxes of 70 mm slides, joined in pairs (Box 33)
    - Sub-Consciously or Other-Wise (25 pairs), and singly (6 slides) (Box 33)
    - Cousins – Friends – Neighbors (27 pairs, with notes) (Box 33)
- Christopher Wren I (Box 34)
  (296 35mm slides)
  - 2 metal slide boxes (Box 34)
    - Wren #1 (134 slides, 1 diagram): The Towers and Spires of Sir Christopher Wren in London (Box 34)
    - Wren #2 (162 slides, 1 diagram): The Towers and Spires of Sir Christopher Wren in London (Box 34)
- Christopher Wren II (Box 35)
  (458 35mm slides)
  - 1 metal slide box (Box 35)
    - Parish Churches, Maps, Drawings (159 slides, 1 handwritten list) (Box 35)
  - 2 boxes slides (299 slides) (Box 35)
    - Wren: 1981, #521-#527; 1982, #548-#552; 1983, #577-#578 (Box 35)
      (also includes some older slides of Wren material)
- Wren et al. (Box 36)
  (Box 1) (69 70mm slides)
- New England after Wren (Box 37)
  (Box 2) (75 70mm slides)
- United States Churches: Connecticut & Rhode Island (Box 38)
  (Box 3) (68 70mm slides)
- United States Churches: Massachusetts & Maine (Box 39)
  (Box 4) (69 70mm slides)
- United States Churches: New Hampshire & Vermont (Box 40)
  (Box 5) (65 70mm slides)
- Notebooks (Box 41)
  - #1: Wren's 50 London Churches: Slides, interior and exterior views, plus "From the Ground-Up" city and U.S. (157, 35mm slides, with notes) (Box 41)
  - #2: Sir Christopher Wren's London Churches (31 8x10 in. prints, with notes) (Box 41)
  - #3: Sir Christopher Wren's Influence on New England Churches (21 8x10 in. prints, with notes and clippings (Box 41)
  - #4: From Meeting-House to Church in New England (36 8 x 10 in. prints, with notes) (Box 41)
  - #5: Anglican Churches in Early New England (19 8x10 in. prints, with notes) (Box 42)
  - #6: New England Neighbors (30 8x10 in. prints) (Box 42)
  - #7: From-the-Ground-Up: U.S.A. (98 35mm slides) (Box 42)
  - #8: From Old England to New England (52 black & white 8x10 in. prints, mounted back to back) (Box 42)
  - Old Meeting-Houses in the New England States (3 8x10 in. prints, plus notes, Xeroxes, church service programs, etc.) (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous New England Churches (12 8x10 in. prints) (Box 43)
  - Gable Fronts in Connecticut (30 black & white 8x10 in. prints, mounted back to back) (Box 43)
  - More Neighbors (25 8x10 in. prints) (Box 43)
  - Unlabeled New England Church photos (42 black & white 8x10 in. prints, mounted back to back) (Box 43)
- 2 Metal slide boxes (Box 44)
  - Churches in Connecticut (173 35mm slides, with notes) (Box 44)
  - More Connecticut, Maine, Rhode Island (198 35mm slides, with notes) (Box 44)
- 3 Slide boxes (Box 45)
  - Churches in New Hampshire and Vermont (229 35mm slides) (Box 45)
  - Churches in Massachusetts (148 35mm slides) (Box 45)
  - New England: Church Details; Church Replacements (46 35mm slides) (Box 45)
- Notebooks (Box 46)
  (19 contact sheets, 85 pages of negatives, 36 prints)
  - England, 120 films, black & white negatives (19 contact sheets and corresponding negatives) (Box 46)
  - England, 120 color (31 pages of negatives) (Box 46)
  - London 1965, 1967, 1969, 1971, 1981, 1982, 1983, 120 color film (35 pages of negatives) (Box 46)
  - Unlabeled notebook of travel photos from Italy and France (36 black & white prints, 8x10 in., mounted back to back) (Box 46)
- Several miscellaneous rolls of film, unidentified (Box 46)